when you open the semens
NX tool this is the interface that you
see here you have new open recently open
Parts assemble touch mode window and
help
let us start with
new when you click on
new you have different options which is
multiaxis deposition inspection
mechatronics concept designer line
Designer work areas and line designer
root model drawing additive
manufacturing Machining line planner and
Manufacturing so here I I'll be
selecting the
model you can select the unit which you
want could be inches or
millimet and here we'll select model
again let me
name this as extrude you can name it
anything based on the project you're
working
on and give
okay so once you click okay
this is the modeling interface that you
get here you have datums where you can
select data plane access or coordinate
system sketch extrude revolve and many
other base
features in the Home tab we'll select
extrude and here we'll select on this
icon which is the sketch section
once you select the sketch section you
can select the plane where you want to
sketch I'm going to select it as the Top
Lane click on the top Lane and give
okay now we are in the sketch mode here
you have different
options like profile rectangle circle
line and so on I'm going to select
rectangle in rectangle we can either go
by two points three points or
Center and
so I'll select the
center click
on
the length I
want and
then place it
here you can
select the
size in case you're not happy with
this selections you can always click on
escape and
then select the sketch which you have
created and click
delete so let's create the rectangle
again click on the
rectangle and here I'll select 70
click on
Tab and then I will select it as 50
angle I'll keep it as zero and click
enter as you can see the rectangle
sketch has been
created I will click on
finish we have exited the sketch
here I will give the thickness as 10
mm and and give
okay you can
see our extrude feature has been
created let us now understand the dats
in the cens andex
tool here we have the datm
plane we can select datm
Axis or the datm coordinate system
let us begin with the datm plane in
order to create the datm plane first
select the surface where the plane needs
to be created I'm going to select this
surface you can always offset from the
surface as shown below here let us keep
it as 0
mm and give it as okay
let us create another datm
plane similarly we'll be selecting the
surface from where we want to offset
this time let us offset it by
mm you can always reverse the
direction as shown and if you want to
increase the number of planes you can
increase it by clicking on this
option so in case you want 10 planes
this is how it would seem right now let
us select two
planes and
click
okay you can see the planes are being
created in the model tree we can always
hide the planes which are not
needed for this
study I'm going to hide all the
planes except these
two you can also hide the extrude
feature or the datm coordinate
system now let us create
an
axis which is offset from this
plane by 10
mm in the reverse
Direction give it as okay select the
axis and
select where the axis needs to be
created so if it is intersection click
on intersection here it asks for the two
objects that are intersecting in our
case it's going to be one the datm
plane and another datm
plane so I have selected both the
intersecting planes and click
okay as you can see the axis has been
created you can always
hide by right
clicking or you can edit the
parameters as shown
below in order to create a new
coordinate system click on this datm
option you can select datm coordinate
system here you have different options
like Dynamic infer origin XO xaxis y AIS
origin and so
on let us start with Dynamic where you
can move the coordinate system wherever
you
want by clicking on the mouse button and
dragging the coordinate you put it in a
specific coordinate system you can
select selected coordinate systems and
select the coordinate system where you
want your new coordinate system to be
placed past and once you done click okay
you can delete this from the model Tree
by right clicking on the model tree
coordinate system and then clicking on
delete same can be done with other
datums where you can delete
them whenever you do not want them you
can also hide the datum planes or
options in the coordinate system by
clicking on
this as you can see even the extrude
feature has been
hidden I'll hide the coordinate system
as
well and the coordinate system is
hidden let us now create a sketch in
seens NX
tool to create a sketch click on the
sketch
icon select the plane where the sketch
needs to be
created I am going to select This
Plane once the plane is selected click
okay so now we have the
reference and the plane so let us create
the sketch
I'm going to use the line
command
click on the
length you
want I'm going to select the line
command
again select the end
point the end point is
seen when it's high highlighted as
shown I'm going to take the vertical
length of 7
mm click
okay you can again select the end
point in case you want to have a
continuous sketch you can always
select this
profile go to
four select
two and select two again so you can just
click
clicking
on the
dimension
once you are okay with all the
dimensions and the sketch
right click and click
okay so our sketch has been
created click
finish to exit as you can see the sketch
has
been in order to create a Revol feature
in cment and
next click on the revolve
feature icon before we go to Revol you
can either create a sketch from the
sketch icon here I have already created
a
sketch as you can
see so I will go directly go to the
Revol
command here we have to select the curve
I'm going to select the sketch that was
created when it is specify Vector we can
either select the
vector from the sketch which is the line
or if you have some other area where the
axis needs to be shown you
can select it for example you can select
the x coordinate from the coordinate
system currently I'll be using the
sketch line as the vector
you can specify the angle if you want it
at
360° you can specify it as 360 as you
can
see the revolve feature is
created I'm going to select it as
180° and you can
see the feature has been created to
180° once your okay with the feature you
can click
okay and the feature will be
created I already have an exclude
feature which was hidden so I'm going to
unhide it
now as you can see both the features are
shown let us now use the whole
feature in order to create create a hole
you can select the whole
feature from the Home
tab here you can select the type of hole
with the simple counter board paper
Reddit Counter sunk whole series and so
on so let me use counter board for
now I will place the dimension as
six the D meter as
8 whole depth
as 6
mm and the
angle as
120° so
click on the plane where you want the
hole to be created so I'm going to
select the face of this
extrude and click
on the hold so in case you want to
change the dimension you can do it over
here so as you can
see the angle gets
changed you can also change the other
parameters based on your requirement
you can create another
hole or if you're satisfied with one you
can click
okay in case you want to change the
position of this hole you can go to the
model tree click on edit
parameters select the dimension that
needs to be
changed and you can change the
same as you can see I have changed the
position of this
ho let us now use the unite feature in
seens
NX to use the unite feature click on the
unite icon in the Home
tab select the target
body I'm going to select this revolve
feature
and R as the another
body you can
preview the
result and then click
okay as you can see unite feature has
been created
here you can edit the same
from
the model
three let us use the extrude feature to
remove material so to in order to do
that click on extrude select the plane
where you want the sketch to be
created
select the sketch feature I'm going to
select the circle and I'm going to type
it as 2 mm as the
diameter once it's satisfactory click on
finish you can change the direction of
the feature by
flipping the
direction you can also change the
distance as shown
below so I changed it to 25
mm you can change it even further let's
say 10 mm and as you can see the feature
has been created click
okay to ex exit the extrude
feature let us now use the
substract
icon in order to use the substract let
me create another extrude or another
body I will hide the datm planes except
dat M
to use extrude
command select sketch
section select the data plane where the
sketch needs to be
created click
okay I'm going to use the
arc we are going to use ARC by Center
and end points
select the
center select the radius as
five and create the
r use line to join these
ends click
okay to finish the sketch
here we will select symmetric
value and take the value as 35
mm click okay to exit the extrude
feature I'm going to hide the DM
plane we have two bodies
now we are going to substract
one from the
other so the body which we retain we'll
keep it as the
target for the tool we will select the
new extrude feature we have
created as you can
see this feature has been removed from
the main
body click okay
exit now let us use the edge blend
command select the edge where
the blend needed to be
created select the
radius and click
okay we will use another
time this time we have options like G2
curvature where you can
see the curvature is not
tangent or we could use the
conic command where we can change the
center
radius so I will it as
and
change this
value that's
five click
okay and as you can
see the edge blend has been
created let us use the chamfer command
in the Home
tab you can see this is the chamfer
command click on it select the edge
where the chamfer needs to be created I
am going to select this Edge select the
distance and it if it's symmetric so I'm
going to create 10
mm and click okay so as you can see the
chamfer has been created we'll create
another
chamfer this time we will select it as
asymmetric and as you can see there are
two distances that are being asked I'm
going to convert this to 20 make this as
10 and click click
okay so this is an asymmetric chamfer
that has been
created let us now create multiple Edge
Blends click on the edge blend
command I'm going to select
circular select the edges which needs to
be created
click on add new
set select the
edges let us make this 10
mm click
okay and as you can see multiple Edge
plants have been created on the extrude
feature
let us use the draft feature to create a
draft on
these
surfaces the draft feature is in the
Home tab you can
see this icon click on the icon select
the vector I'm going to select the Z
axis as the vector you have to select
the stationary phas this is the flat
phas from where the draft is going to be
created selected the stationary phas now
we will go to the faces to draft select
faces we'll start by selecting this
pH and as you can see the draft is
created we will edit the angle you can
put it as 15°
I will place it
as
5° click
okay and you can see that the draft has
been
created going to hide the sketch and you
can
see how the draft has been
created let us now learn about the shell
feature in seens NX
in order to create the shell of this
particular
model go to the Home tab here you will
go to the Shell
feature you have options of open and
closed so you can see what these two
options mean in the preview I'm going to
select open select the face
click
okay this thickness is too high for this
particular model I'm going to change the
thickness to 2 mm and you can
see since it is possible to create the
shell the shell feature is going to be
created
let us now use the pattern
feature let me create an extrude feature
on this
plane I will choose
this use the circle
command and create a
circle finish
I'm going to give the distance as 4
mm make it 5
mm click
okay so this extrude feature is going to
be patterned in order to pattern select
the feature to be
patterned select on the pattern feature
icon I'm going to select linear there
are other options like circular polygon
spiral along General and
reference let us start with the linear
we have to specify the vector or the
direction to be patterned
it I am going to select this
direction we
have five from five count I will convert
it into four count make the distance
between each pattern as 8
mm and click
okay as you can see a
patterned let us now learn how to use
the mirror feature in cens
NX in order to use the mirror feature go
to the Home tab click on the mirror
feature select the feature that needs to
be
mirrored I'm going to select the Revol
Sev as the feature to be
mirrored you have to select plane along
which the mirror has to be
performed I'm going to select the datm
plane
4 select the
plane you can use show result to look at
the preview
if it is satisfactory click
okay the mirror feature has been
created let us now use the move and
delete commands in seen and
next I will hide this St temp
planate to use the move command in the
Home tab go to the move
icon select the pH which
needs to be
moved and specify the
distance I'm going to say 10
mm and as you can see the phase which
was a drafted
phe gets offset
it by a distance of 10
mm you can deselect The Face
Finders in case you want to
select a different face right now I'm
going to keep it at this
distance angle is zero you can change
the angle as well so as you can
see the angle is specified from the
face if it is in a different direction
you can use
negative and click
okay now let us use the delete command
click on
delete here I'm going to remove this
ho so select
the
face and as you can
see the hole has been removed click
okay and we have removed this
hole now let us understand the offset
command in seens
NX in the Home tab go to the
offset here you can select the face
we are selecting a single
phas you can see there are different
options you have single phas tangent
face adjacent faces feature face region
boundary faces BS or pocket rib faces or
slot for faces let us start with the
single phas I'm going to offset it by 5
mm and as you can see similar to move
you have off set of
5mm and click
okay but right now let us
try to use another offset
option so I'm going to
undo the offset which was created let us
create another offset but this time let
us
select tangent faces
so I'm going to select this and
this and right now I'm giving an offset
5 mm you can see the feature has
scaled or ponded by 5 mm since we had
selected all the three
faces click
okay and as you can see the offset has
been
created let us now create a new drawing
in order to create a new drawing click
on new in the seens NX
tool here select
drawing select the unit millimet inches
meters let us select
millimet select the drawing
size I'm going to go with A4 size you
can name the drawing I'm going to name
it as
exercise Creator
Zone click okay
here you can give the input so first is
should uh let me call it as
Xyz gr
by you can name
it and going to give it
as subscribe
app so you can give the check by
approved by drawn by
names uh once you have created the
template which is the standard template
from
seens you can select the base view so
since I do not have any models open in
the session I would like to
open the same from
my
desktop click on the sheet you can get
the projection
views in any angle you want so I'm going
to go
with perpendicular
projections once your projections are
done you can close this you have
your views created you can place these
views by clicking on the box as shown
below and dragging them wherever you
want let us now create a detailed view
in seens NX
drawing to create a detailed view go to
the Home tab click on detailed View
you can select the type of detail view
you want circular rectangle by Corners
rectangle by Center and corner so I'm
going to choose circular select the
center point where the detail view needs
to be created we're going to select this
point specify the boundary you can
rag look at the size I'm okay with this
size so I'll click
okay and select the place where you want
the detailed view to be I'm going to
position it
here click close to exit the detailed
view you can
move The annotation as
shown you
can position
The
annotation by dragging
it let us now create a sectional view in
seens n
x first I'll make some space for the
sectional
view next in the Home tab go to the
section
view in this icon you have different
options like select existing or
dynamic since it's a new one let us go
with Dynamic we have to specify the
location of the
section I'm going to position this
section where I want it so I will select
this area
in this view we can take any angle we
want so let
us take it in
this vertical
Direction so once the sectional view is
created you can move
it I'm going
to delete this detail view to show you
the sectional
view in order to delete a view select
the view and click on
delete so as you can see the sectional
view that is section BB has been
created we
can double click on The
annotation to change the height Factor
as you can see it has been
changed let us now create a section
which is not straight section but if we
have a section
which changes the
direction we can do that so before we do
that I will delete this section to make
room click
yes go to section
line
select stand alone select the section
view create the profile along which the
section needs to be created so this is
not going to be a straight line we will
create it as shown
below and save
finish
apply and you can see the section has
been
created let's go to the section view so
that we can create a section view from
this section
c in order to create the section view we
will select
existing select this
section drag
it out and you have the section over
here
close move it to the top so that the
section is
visible let us now understand
dimensioning in seens NX drawing
here we have a
drawing here are few drawing
views and we are going to Dimension the
same in order to Dimension go to the
Home tab click on
rapid for a quick
dimensioning here I'm going to select
the
diameter click on the
diameter and you can see with the
dimension has been created in order to
change the format of this Dimension
double click on the
dimension here you can
change the style I'm going to select
horizontal text you can make
it
into different
tolerancing you can also change change
from diameter to
radius click close to
exit I'm going to push this Dimension to
the
side so that I will create another one
using the linear
command here I'll be selecting
[Music]
two
phases so I'll select this do this in
order to do that the first object will
be this select the second object and
click on the object that the dimension
needs to be
created click
close exit in order to
change the
dimension I will round it off to zero
decimals so you can do that here you can
also type
in any notes if there are
any so you
can make all these
changes using
these
options so you can go horizontal as well
going to take it back to Vertical drag
it out so that it's clearly
visible we can also CAG this
Dimension back to where it
was so this is how you create basic
dimensioning I'm going to create another
one with
angles it is the same step where you
select
first object and then you select the
second object and then you can show the
dimension click close exit in order to
push it outside you can
always use
this here we have other
options we have call outs and ordinates
in the dimension
tab you can
also take chamfer by picking on this
thickness Arc Length perimeter
Dimension let us now create note in
seens NX drawing in order to create a
note in the Home tab go to note
here you can
click you can type the note you want to
type I'm going to call it as drawing
for
exercise
purpose click on the location where you
want to know not to
be and click close so as you can see the
note is created here you can position it
anywhere you
want
and place it in the
location let us now understand how to
add G gdn symbols in seens NX
in order to add the control frame the
feature control
frame we can go to the Home tab and
select the feature control
frame we have to position it where we
want I'm going to position it here and
then I'm going to select
leader and select the terminating object
so it's going to be on this Sur
F I'm going to give it as
okay I'm going
to change this
position as you can see we can change it
wherever we want it to
be and once we have
selected the location click
okay here I'm going to change
change from
straightness flatness so I'll go here
and here you can select if it is
composite feature control you can go
with this option or if it's single let's
go with this we can select the different
tolerances like
position
flatness profile of a surface
angle and many more I'll go with
flatness select the
dimension I'm going to give it as 2 mm
you can also specify if it's least
material condition maximum material
condition in this case we'll keep it as
none we can if it was a diameter you
could have position given it as diameter
and square if it was a square
you can also add different symbols that
are
available once you're done with this you
can go with
different like primary secondary lary
dams again I'm going to keep it as
none once this is
satisfactory click on okay to exit
as you can
see a gdnt symbol has been
created in the
drawing you can again position it
wherever you
want let us create a datum feature
symbol in the seens NX drawing in order
to create a datm feature symbol go to
the Home tab click on the datum feature
symbol
specify the
location and in case you need a leader
add a
leader
position the symbol and click close
exit as you can
see you
can create a datm feature symbol and
position it after that
by
moving the
symbol in the
drawing now let us add some symbols to
our drawing
views first let us see how we can add a
surface finish symbol in the Home tab
click on the surface finish symbol
select the surface where the symbol
needs to be added I'm going to select
this surface click on the
surface you can choose open open
modifier
or any other
option you can also add
X I'm just going to
show in the upper side as well as the
lower
text you can add
waviness and you can
see how the symbol looks
like also in case you want to add a
balloon click on the balloon you can
type the number for the
balloon in the leader
click on add new
leader
select the location and click on close
to exit in case you do not need a leader
click on the
balloon enter the
text and directly click on the
drawing click close to exit
let us now understand how we can create
table in seens NX
drawing let me clear some
space so I'll just delete these
views in order to create a table go to
tabular note in the Home
tab click
on the number of columns needed I'm
going to give it as
five make this as
three and then column width you can
change it going to make it
20 and click on the location where you
want it close if no long if you
need no longer need any more
tables click on this
and you can type the data you
want I'm going to type a serial
number and here you can type
numbers similarly you can manually input
all the data as shown in this video
let us now understand how we can do
surface modeling in seens
NX I will open a new
model you can select model and any units
you need I'll be selecting
millimeters and I will name this as
surface
modeling
exercise click
okay our
file has
opened now I will start with creating a
sketch I will select the front plane
click on okay
and I will start start with an
arc I will change the dimension to
radius of
50 and then I'll see
finish so once my arc is create it I
will go to
surface so let us start with
extrude and you can
see how my
extrude looks like I will give it as 25
mm and give
okay next I will create another sketch
and show you how the swept command works
go to the Home tab click on the sketch
now I'll select the Top
Lane I will
create an arc
again this time it will be from this
point and take it like this
once again I go to the surface tab click
on
swep now that there is nothing selected
here I will
select this
curve and for the guide I'll select it
as
this you can see
our swep has used this as a guide in
using the section which was created
earlier I'll give it as
okay let us now understand the true C
command in this semens NX surface
modeling first let us create another
datm
plane I will offset it from this at
about 80
mm click
okay I'll select this datum and I will
start a
sketch I will make an arc
close
Okay I select the dimension as 30 mm
radius and then finish the
application next I'll go to surface
select through
curves and in through
curves I will
first
select the the curve middle Mouse
button and select the next one as you
can
see
the surface seems to be colliding this
is because the points needs to be
changed needs to be
flipped so I will cancel this
selection I'll go to through curves
again
select the surface and while selecting
the other surface I'll Al select this
area middle bouse button and
click now you can see the surface is
Blended
well and the through curve has been
created I'll click okay
exit and the surface
as let us now use the offset surface and
the thicken command in the semens NX
surface
mode
first let's try
Picken we
can incre Eon the
Surface by selecting the surface
increase the
thickness also multiple faces can be
selected as
shown click okay create the thickened
surface we can use
offset so before I use offset I will
hide the
thicken and I will only show the
faces click on
offset select the face that needs to be
offset set it I'll make it
as 10 mm and in the opposite
direction as you can see the offset has
been
created multiple surfaces can also be
selected in this
case what I will be
selecting
only this
surface click it as 10 opposite
direction and click
okay so the offset has been
created and in case I want these two
surface as well I will make another
offset and
10 along with this surface and give it
as okay
I will hide these two offset
surfaces and I
will merge the spaces in order to merge
it click on
Sue select this first sheet
body and the second sheet
body click okay so as you can see the
these two surfaces has been
combined or Sue
together I'll create
another shoe but this time I'll select
the other fa
surface and you can see the
complete surface
sheet is Con concluded as
one let us use the extend sheet command
in the surface modeling in seens n
x so go to the surface tab here you will
have extend sheet click on the extend
sheet you can
select the edge which you want it to be
extended have selected this Edge select
the
dimension which the extension needs to
be done and click
okay you can
also
create an extension to curved
surfaces as shown below I'm going to
reduce the
length it's going to follow the same
path as the original
surface click okay exit
and you can see
in order to measure a feature
in seens NX modeling
tool go to analysis
tab click on
measure here you can
select the area or the surface which you
need to measure so as you can see the
data is provided like area perimeter
radius centroid you can also filter the
the measurement
data and only select the ones which you
need click okay once done in case you
want to measure the edge the steps are
similar we will have to select the
edge
and can get the
dimensions of
the edge
so undo the
filter and you can see that the
dimension is provided which is radius of
3.5 and here the
surface is having radius
you have to remove this so you can see
the radius of the surface which is 2.5
let us now learn how to create a new
part and edit the display
color we will create this part and later
use this part for the assembly in seens
NX tool I'm going to name this part as
top
click
okay here I'm going to start with
Sketch going to select the top plane
click
okay select rectangle going to rectang
use rectangle by by
Center I'm going to add the
dimensions for this
rectangle you can click on
the line in case you haven't given the
dimension
initially so I'll click on the
highlighted
line and double click to change the
dimension here here I'm going to make it
as
50 so this is 150 by 50
mm I'll add another rectangle
here we will be using the
trim command to later edit this
so you can use
trim to delete the
unnecessary
lines
similarly I'll be creating another
rectangle on the side by
20 tab click 20 and enter
use trim
again so this will be the
top
part
and
finish I'm going to extrude this at 15
mm
okay so once this part is
ready we will will go to the editing the
display in the display tab click on Ed
edit object display select the object
click okay here you have color you can
select any color you want I'm going to
go with uh blue click okay
apply and okay so as you can see the
body display has been
changed click
save to save this
model we will now create a new
model create a new model click on
new I'm going to call this as
leg click okay
I have to select sketch I'm going to
select the right plane click
okay here I'm going to
use the
rectangle
with Corner
point Sorry Center Point
I
will select
it at this
distance and make
this
as 15
mm we make this distance
as
now I will create the
legs which is using
lines we select
it up
to 15
on one
side going to give it at an
angle make it as 75 mm and angle
as 240
use this end
point create another
line I'll do the same on this side
P
mm keep
going so length I'll keep it as
75 AB
300 now I'll trim the corners you can
use the
corner to
select the areas which are needed I'll
use trim to remove the
unnecessary
lines click on finish
extrude so I'm going to give it as 10 mm
extrude and
okay I will also change the display go
to edit display select the
object click okay select the color we
desire want to go
with red
apply
okay we can now create the
assembly let us go to
new go click on
assembly we'll name
this
assembly as whatever we
desire click
okay to open the
assembly here
click on
Open click on the part that you need to
open click on
at position
component keep straints and then
okay let us now add fix constraint to
this
part you can select on fix from the
assemblies we have to select the
object selected the
object and click on
okay now you can
see this part is fixed to the current
position let us now add another
component to
this assembly
we will select the part as
leg click on the anchor as
absolute here we will have to
select the position where we want to
click we can either use a coordinate
system or place the component at
Absolute absolute
origin or place the component at
Absolute origin of the displayed
assembly and place the component at
the coordinate system that we
have so I'm going to
select this and
position the part where I want it to be
click
okay I would also like to give
constraints so let us give such
constraint
for this
surface and the inner
surface as you can see the part is
positioned
itself
okay we will give another touch
constraint which will be
coinciding this
surface with this surface
click okay when
done we would now give another touch
constraint which will coincide these two
surfaces but
since the first constraint is
obstructing
this we will have
to cancel
it
and we
can
delete the constraint by right clicking
on the constraint to be deleted
let us use
parallel and you can
see the constraint gets
created again if you want to delete the
constraint you have to click on the
constraint select the constraint
and
delete let us now understand the move
component command in seens NX
assembly click on move from the
assemblies you have to select the
component select the component then you
have to specify the
orientation so this z-axis would be my
orientation and click on
okay to
exit I will give touch
command or constraint on this assembly
and select the
components
apply and
okay let us now understand the auto
align
constraint here I had added a touch
constraint and as you can
see this is the touch constraint I will
delete this and show you how how Auto
align constraint works we are going to
select auto align
constraint we're going to select the two
objects that need to be
aligned and I can as you can
see the
component has aligned
itself click close to
exit let us now understand pattern
component command in the seens NX
assembly
interface so we want this part on the
other
side I will use pattern
component the count will be
two I know this distance is 150 mm and
the groove is about 10 mm so 150 - 10 mm
we would keep it as 140
mm and this would be the component which
we are going to pattern we have to
specify the vector or the direction
where the pattern needs to be
created so this xais is the direction
where I want it I will click on X and as
you can
see the component is added on the other
side click
okay to
exit as you can see the simple
assembly of a bench has been created